{
    "questionModals": [
      {
        "question": "In a mortar, the binding material is",
        "answers": ["Cement", "Sand", "Surkhi", "cinder"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Wrought iron contains carbon upto",
        "answers": ["0.25%", "0.75%", "1.25%", "2%"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Pick up the polymineralic rock from the following:",
        "answers": ["Quartz sand", "Granite", "Magnesite", "Pure Gypsum"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Ultimate strength to cement is provided by",
        "answers": ["Tricalcium silicate", "Di-calcium silicate", "Tri-calcium aluminate", "Tetra calcium alumino ferrite"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Elastomers can extend upto ....... times their original dimensions",
        "answers": ["5", "7", "10", "100"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Bitumen felt is",
        "answers": ["used as water proofing material", "used as damp proofing material", "made from bitumen and hessian fibres", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "In the cement the compound quickest to react with water, is",
        "answers": ["Tricalcium silicate", "Dicalcium silicate", "Tricalcium aluminate", "Tetra-calcium alumino-ferrite"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Bitumen felt is",
        "answers": ["used as water proofing material", "used as damp proofing material", "made from bitumen and hessian fibres", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "The initial setting time of lime-pozzolana, is",
        "answers": ["5 minutes", "30 minutes", "90 minutes", "120 minutes"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "The clay to be used for manufacturing bricks for a large project, is dugout and allowed to weather throughout",
        "answers": ["the monsoon", "the winter", "the summer", "not necessary"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The rocks which are formed due to cooling of magma at a considerable depth from earth's surface are called",
        "answers": ["Plutonic rocks", "Hypabyssal rocks", "Volcanic rocks", "Igneous rocks"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Quartzite is a",
        "answers": ["metamorphic rock", "argillaceous rock", "calcareous rock", "Igneous rocks"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The variety of pig iron used for manufacture of wrought iron, is",
        "answers": ["Bessemer pig", "Grey or foundry pig", "White forge pig", "Mottled pig"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Sand stone is a",
        "answers": ["metamorphic rock", "sedimentary rock", "calcareous rock", "Igneous rock"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Stainless steel contains",
        "answers": ["18% of chromuim and 8% nickel", "8% of chromium and 18% of nickel", "12% of chromium and 36% of nickel", "36% of chromium and 12% of nickel"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Pick up the hypahypabyssal rock from the following:",
        "answers": ["Dolerite", "Granite", "Basalt", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Kaolin is chemically classified as ",
        "answers": ["metamorphic rock", "argillaceous rock", "calcareous rock", "Igneous rocks"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Which one of the following is acid resistant asbestos:",
        "answers": ["actinolite asbestos", "anthophylite asbestos", "crocidolite asbestos", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Due to attack of dry rot, the timber",
        "answers": ["cracks", "shrinks", "reduces to powder", "hardens"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Brittleness of cold is due to an excess of",
        "answers": ["sulphur", "phosphorus", "silicon", "carbon"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "For the manufacture of Portland cement, the proportions of raw materials used, are",
        "answers": ["lime 63% ; silica 22% ; other ingredients 15%", "silica 40% ; lime 40% ; other ingredients 20%", "lime 22% ; silica 63% ; other ingredients 15%", "silica 70% ; lime 20% ; other ingredients 10%"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Gniess is obtained from",
        "answers": ["igneous rocks", "metamorphic rocks", "sedimentary rocks", "sedimentary metamorphic rocks"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "The rocks formed by gradual deposition, are called",
        "answers": ["sedimentary rocks", "igneous rocks", "metamorphic rocks", "none of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Galvanising means covering iron with a thin coat of",
        "answers": ["Zinc", "Copper", "Tin", "Coaltar"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Sewer pipes are made of",
        "answers": ["earthen ware", "stone ware", "refractory clay", "terracota"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The commonly used colour pigment in paints, is",
        "answers": ["ambers", "iron oxide", "lamp black", "all the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Varnish is a transparent or semi-transparent solution of resinuous substances in",
        "answers": ["alcohol", "linseed", "turpentine", "all the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Initial setting time of cement for asbestos cement products should be not less than",
        "answers": ["30 minutes", "60 minutes", "90 minutes", "120 minutes"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The variety of pig iron used for the manufacture of steel by Bessemer process, is",
        "answers": ["Bessemer pig", "Grey pig", "White forge pig", "Mottled pig"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "For filling cracks in masonry structures, the type of bitumen used, is",
        "answers": ["cut-back bitumen", "bitumen-emulsion", "plastic bitumen", "blown bitumen"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Vanadium steel is generally used for",
        "answers": ["railway switches and crossing", "axles and springs", "bearing balls", "magnets"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The process of manufacturing steel by heating short lengths of wrought iron bars mixed with charcoal in fire clay crucibles and collecting the molten iron into moulds, is known as",
        "answers": ["Cementation process", "Crucible process", "Bessemer process", "Open hearth process"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The rocks in which clay predominates, are called",
        "answers": ["sillicious rocks", "argillaceous rocks", "calcareous rocks", "igneous rocks"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "A badly mixed cement concrete results in",
        "answers": ["segregation", "bleeding", "honey combing", "none of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Chemically, marble is known as",
        "answers": ["sillicious rock", "argillaceous rock", "calcareous rock", "metamorphic rock"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Inner part of a timber log surrounding the pith, is called",
        "answers": ["sapwood", "cambium layer", "heart wood", "barkwood"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The filler used in plastic bitumen, is",
        "answers": ["shale powder", "asbestos powder", "talc powder", "plastic powder"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Refractory bricks are used for",
        "answers": ["retaining walls", "columns", "piers", "combustion chambers"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "The rock generally used for roofing, is",
        "answers": ["granite", "slate", "marble", "basalt"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "A piece of sawn timber whose cross-sectional dimensions exceed 5 cm, in one direction and 20 cm in the other direction, is called a",
        "answers": ["cant", "deal", "baulk", "strip"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Which type of cement from the following commonly used for canal linings",
        "answers": ["sulphate resisting cement", "rapid hardening cement", "quick setting cement", "pozzuolana cement"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Mastic asphalt is generally used for",
        "answers": ["damp proof course", "water proof layer", "both (a) and (b)", "none of these"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The most fire resistant paints are",
        "answers": ["enamel paints", "aluminium paints", "cement paints", "asbestos paints"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "If P is the percentage of water required for normal consistency, water to be added for determination of initial setting time, is",
        "answers": ["0.75P", "0.80P", "0.85P", "0.9P"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "A pug mill is used for",
        "answers": ["softening brick earth", "moulding brick earth", "tempering brick earth", "all the above"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The commonly used lime in white washing, is",
        "answers": ["white lime", "fat lime", "hydraulic lime", "quick lime"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Pick up the plutonic rock from the following:",
        "answers": ["granite", "Dolerite", "obsidian", "basalt"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The lime which contains mainly calcium oxide and slacks with water, is",
        "answers": ["white lime", "fat lime", "hydraulic lime", "quick lime"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Seasoning is",
        "answers": ["a process of removing sap", "creosoting", "painting with sodium silicate", "coating with tar"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Rocks formed due to alteration of original structure due to heat and excessive pressure are called",
        "answers": ["sedimentary rocks", "igneous rocks", "metamorphic rocks", "none of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "For slaking of 10 kg of CaO, the theoretical amount of water is",
        "answers": ["2.2 kg", "3.2 kg", "1.5 kg", "5.6 kg"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Clay and silt content in a good brick earth must be at least",
        "answers": ["50%", "40%", "30%", "20%"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Bessemer process is used for the manufacture of",
        "answers": ["Pig iron", "Wrought iron", "cast iron", "steel"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "The portion of the brick without a triangular corner equal to half the width and half the length, is called",
        "answers": ["queen closer", "king closer", "bevelled Closer", "squint brick"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Which one of the following is an air binding material ?",
        "answers": ["Gypsum", "Acid-resistant cement", "Quick lime", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "A good quality stone absorbs water less than",
        "answers": ["5%", "10%", "15%", "25%"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Plywood is made from",
        "answers": ["common timber", "bamboo fibre", "teak wood", "sal wood"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Soundness test of cement determines",
        "answers": ["quality of free lime", "ultimate strength", "durability", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Minimum of 40% of iron, is available in",
        "answers": ["Magnetite", "Red haemetite", "Limonite", "Black band"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "If the iron ore contains clay as an impurity, the flux added during calcination, is",
        "answers": ["clay", "lime stone", "argillaceous iron ore", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Cast steel is manufactured by",
        "answers": ["Cementation process", "Crucible process", "Bessemer process", "Open hearth process"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "For the manufacture of plywood, veneers are placed so that grains of adjacent veneers",
        "answers": ["run at right angles", "parallel", "inclined at 45°", "inclined at 60°"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Geologically, marble is known as",
        "answers": ["sedimentary rock", "igneous rock", "metamorphic rock", "stratified rock"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The commonly used drying oil for oil paints, is",
        "answers": ["kerosine oil", "accetate of lead", "linseed oil", "olive oil"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Initial setting of cement is caused due to",
        "answers": ["Tri-calcium silicate", "Di-calcium silicate", "Tri-calcium aluminate", "Tetra calcium alumino ferrite"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The foliated structure is very common in",
        "answers": ["sedimentary rocks", "igneous rocks", "metamorphic rocks", "none of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Turpentine oil is used in paints as",
        "answers": ["thinner", "vehicle", "base", "drier"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The hardest rock is",
        "answers": ["marble", "diamond", "talc", "quartz"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Wrought iron is used for",
        "answers": ["structural works in beams", "small sized water pipes", "columns and struts", "none of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The timber having maximum resistance against white ants, is obtained from",
        "answers": ["chir", "shisham", "sal", "teak"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Knots in timber are",
        "answers": ["defects caused by crushing fibres", "splits radiating from the centre", "speckled strains", "signs of branches cut off"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Lime concrete is generally used for",
        "answers": ["wall foundations", "flooring at ground level", "both (a) and (b)", "neither (a) nor (b)"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Bituminous fells are used for",
        "answers": ["covering A.C. sheets", "covering sloping roofs", "D.P.C", "none of these"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Duco is one of the patent forms of",
        "answers": ["emulsion paints", "bituminous paints", "aluminium paints", "cellulose paints"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Bulking of sand is caused due to",
        "answers": ["surface moisture", "air voids", "viscosity", "all the above"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The normal curing period for lime mortar, is:",
        "answers": ["1 day", "3 days", "7 days", "14 days"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The type of steel used for precision levelling staff, is",
        "answers": ["Titanium steel", "Carbon steel", "Invar", "Stainless steel"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "German silver is an alloy of",
        "answers": ["zinc, lead and nickel", "copper, nickel and zinc", "copper, brass and zinc", "brass, silver and zinc"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Dextrin is",
        "answers": ["animal glue", "starch glue", "albumin glue", "rubber based adhesive"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "For the manufacture of stainless steel, steel is mixed with",
        "answers": ["chromium", "nickel", "tungsten", "none of these"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Stones used for ornamental work must be",
        "answers": ["soft", "hard", "light", "heavy"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The presence of original rounded surface on the manufactured piece of timber, is called",
        "answers": ["Wane", "Torn grain", "Diagonal grain", "Chipmark"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Smith's test of stones is performed to find out",
        "answers": ["the compressive strength of the stone", "the presence of soluble matter of stone", "the hardness of the stone", "the toughness of the stone"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The cracks caused by shrinkage of the exterior surface of the wood exposed to atmosphere, are called:",
        "answers": ["radial shakes", "heart shakes", "wind cracks", "twisted fibres"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The process of decarbonising the pig iron completely and then adding proper percentage of carbon for manufacturing steel, is called",
        "answers": ["Cementation process", "crucible process", "Bessemer process", "Open hearth process"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "In paints, the pigment is responsible for",
        "answers": ["durability", "colour", "glassy face", "water repulsion"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The operation of removal of impurities or clay adhering to iron ores, is known as",
        "answers": ["dressing", "calcination", "roasting", "smelting"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Portland cement manufactured from pure white chalk and clay but free from iron-oxide, is known as",
        "answers": ["quick setting cement", "rapid hardening cement", "white cement", "low heat Portland cement"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Dry rot",
        "answers": ["cracks the timber", "reduces the timber to powder", "reduces the strength of timber", "spoils the appearance of timber"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Pozzolana (or surkhi) is used in lime",
        "answers": ["to impart hydraulicity", "to prevent shrinkage", "to decrease the cost of construction", "to decrease the setting time"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Mastic asphalt is normally used for",
        "answers": ["Sound Insulation", "water proofing", "fire proofing", "none of these"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The standard size of brick as per NBC 109-1994 is",
        "answers": ["270mm x 155mm x 97mm", "240mm x 115mm x 57mm", "215mm x 105mm x 57mm", "210mm x 190mm x 90mm"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "A piece of timber whose thickness and width are respectively 5 cm and 10 cm is called",
        "answers": ["slate", "plank", "board", "strip"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Pig iron is manufactured from the ores by",
        "answers": ["dressing", "calcination and roasting", "smelting", "all the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Age of a tree may be ascertained by",
        "answers": ["radius of its stem", "circumference of its stem", "number of branches", "number of annual rings"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "The portion of a brick cut to form angles other than right angles in plan, is known as",
        "answers": ["queen closer", "king closer", "squint brick", "closer"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The initial setting time of hydraulic lime, is",
        "answers": ["30 minutes", "60 minutes", "90 minutes", "120 minutes"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "PVC stands for",
        "answers": ["plastic very compact", "polythene vinyl chloride", "polythene vinyl carbon", "polythene vanadium carbide"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "Generally wooden moulds are made from",
        "answers": ["ply wood", "shisham wood", "deodar wood", "teak wood"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The cement becomes unsound by the presence of excess",
        "answers": ["sulphur", "magnesia", "lime", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "The kiln which may work throughout the year, is",
        "answers": ["Bull's trench kiln", "Clamp", "Hoffman's kiln", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "A volatile substance added to a paint to make its application easy and smooth, is known as",
        "answers": ["base", "solvent", "vehicle", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 1
      },
      {
        "question": "The percentage of water for normal consistency, is",
        "answers": ["10% to 20%", "20% to 25%", "25% to 35%", "35% to 45%"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Bitumen is generally obtained from",
        "answers": ["synthetic material", "organic material", "petroleum product", "coal"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "The steel which contains fissures and cavities, is manufactured by",
        "answers": ["Cementation process", "Crucible process", "Bessemer process", "Open hearth process"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "Pick up the volcanic rock from the following:",
        "answers": ["Granite", "Dolerite", "Basalt", "all of the above"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "In stone masonry, stones (stratified rocks) are so placed that the direction of pressure to the plane of bedding is",
        "answers": ["right angles", "parallel", "45°", "60°"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The most durable varnish is",
        "answers": ["water varnish", "spirit varnish", "turpentine varnish", "oil varnish"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Softer variety of steel may be obtained by",
        "answers": ["Cementation process", "Open hearth process", "Bessemer process", "crucible process"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      },
      {
        "question": "Strength of cement concrete primarily depends upon",
        "answers": ["quality of water", "quantity of aggregate", "quantity of cement", "water-cement ratio"],
        "correctIndex": 3
      },
      {
        "question": "Rapid hardening cement contains",
        "answers": ["Tri-calcium silicate", "Tri-calcium aluminate", "Tetra-calcium alumino-ferrite", "Dicalcium silicate"],
        "correctIndex": 0
      },
      {
        "question": "The cast iron when heated to red heat with powdered red haemetite in an oven for increasing its toughness, is converted to",
        "answers": ["grey cast iron", "white cast iron", "mottled cast iron", "toughed cast iron"],
        "correctIndex": 2
      }
    ]
  }
  